<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands settlement mistaken, or, A short survey of a pamphlet called England's settlement upon the two solid foundations of the peoples civil and religious liberties, pleading for a toleration of all religions wherein his ten arguments for toleration are confuted as so many sophisms and fallacies / by a well-willer to both civil and religious liberties of the people.</title>
            <author>Well-willer to both civil and religious liberties of the people.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09546682</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09546682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1330:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands settlement mistaken, or, A short survey of a pamphlet called England's settlement upon the two solid foundations of the peoples civil and religious liberties, pleading for a toleration of all religions wherein his ten arguments for toleration are confuted as so many sophisms and fallacies / by a well-willer to both civil and religious liberties of the people.</title>
                  <author>Well-willer to both civil and religious liberties of the people.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D. Maxwell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Englands settlement upon the two solid foundations of the peoples civil and religious liberties.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
               <term>Political rights --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43574:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> SETTLEMENT MISTAKEN: OR A Short Survey of a Pamphlet CALLED ENGLAND'S SETTLEMENT <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the two ſolid Foundations of the Peoples</hi> Civil <hi>and</hi> Religious LIBERTIES.</p>
            <p>PLEADING For a Toleration of all Religions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> His Ten ARGUMENTS for Toleration are Confuted, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sophiſms and Fallacies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Well-willer to both Civil and Religious Liberties of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>D. Maxwell,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43574:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43574:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS <hi>SETTLEMENT MISTAKEN,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Author of <hi>Englands Settlement,</hi> is by many wiſe men thought to be a diſguiſed <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> or a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited Sectary:</hi> '[The voice is <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice, but the hands are the hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi>] He perſonates in his words, a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> putting himſelf amongſt us, as one of us, but his Deſign is, under a pretence of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of all Religions;</hi> as to aſperſe our both Church and State, with the ugly crime of Perſecution; ſo eſpecially to plead for Liberty of Conſcience to Papiſts and Recuſants, as ſhall be made appear in ventilation of the Tract it ſelf. He hath ſcraped together, out of ſeveral Sectarian Books or Pamphlets, <hi>Anabaptiſts, Levellers, Fifth Monarchy</hi> men, &amp;c. no leſs then ten <hi>Arguments,</hi> which as they are very plauſible (like a fair picture upon courſe cloath afar off) to ſimple and weak apprehenſions; ſo being looked on nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hand, and touched by the hand of a ſolid underſtanding, are like the Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> which touched turn to aſhes, and prove but ſo many thred-bare <hi>Sophiſms,</hi> or tranſparent Fallacies, often confuted. His method of proceeding (that they that have not his Tract may ſee what he hath ſaid, and judg the better of it) is this:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43574:3"/>1. He ſeemes, out of pity and compaſſion to the Nation, (whiles he is ſecretly piling up his barrels of Gunpowder, (once more) under the Parliament Houſe, to blow it up, by procuring an <hi>Act of Toleration</hi> for all Religions) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie, and bewaile out paſt and preſent miſeries, as the <hi>Amazement</hi> of the world, and the <hi>intolerable burden</hi> of <q>the nation; for ſo he ſayes; [They experience, that their ſo much talk'd of, and ſo often promiſed liberty, has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nothing but real and almoſt intolerable Slavery: their plenty has been turned into miſerable poverty; and their peace,</q> into endleſs troubles] How truly let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers judg.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>He tells us (what indeed we find) [There has been a curſe upon the Government theſe ten years; it hath been all that time a rolling, like <hi>Syſiphus</hi> ſtone, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant like the Moon: The judgments of God have been very terrible and univerſal, both over Church and State, and have gone round over all ſorts of Perſons, as well of high as low degree. For the late Engliſh Church hath been quite overturned, the King himſelf, the Head thereof, tragically beheaded, and his poſterity rigorouſly excluded. The Nobillity is in a manner degraded, the houſe of Peeres aboliſhed, the Ancient Gentry ſlighted, the Marchants and Commons, by decay of trade, and by the unhappy conjunction of extraordinary Taxes, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed, Yea the Parliaments themſelves, have not gone without ſome chaſtiſement. For their own hired ſervants, have oftener, than once, lifted their heels againſt them, and without any lawful Authority, but according to their own pleaſures or intereſts, have diſſolved, called, anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated and revived them. Only the Souldiers, whom God hath uſed as Inſtruments to puniſh others, may ſeem to have gone hitherto unpuniſhed]</q> How true this is alſo let others judg.</p>
            <p n="3">3 He ſeems to take upon him to be a prophet, and to foretel what is like to come upon thoſe (the Army) that <q>have not yet ſmarted: for ſo he ſays: [Every thing muſt have its time, to come to maturity: and God Almighty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43574:3"/>has begun already to manifeſt his judgments, upon ſome of their principal Heads and firſt Movers: <hi>O. P.</hi> his poſterity, and others of his chief Officers &amp;c. which may ſerve for a warning for all the reſt, to prevent Gods Judgments, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt they ſall heavily upon them,</q> here, or hereafter] They may do well to conſider it, and lay it to heart</p>
            <p n="4">4. Having done this, he inquires into the cauſes of theſe judgments and divine viſitations, and our ſo long unſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <q>and reſolves well in general, [Some very heinous ſin or ſins have provoked them; but what theſe ſins are in particular, is not ſo eaſie to determine, to every mans ſatisfaction.] Yet he goes on, in the ſearch of them, and firſt gives us his own judgment upon the caſe; [it may probably be affirmed, if not averred as a certain truth, that Soul-tyranny, or coercive power over mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is the principal ſin that hath drawn down theſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from heaven, (for ſome reaſons,) For firſt it is an heinous ſin in it ſelf, (as he will ſhew ſhortly) and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be exerciſed againſt the true Religion:]</q> Before we hear the reſt, conſider this; Firſt, he ſhould have ſaid, Soul Tyranny is an heinous ſin, (not eſpecially, but) only when it is exerciſed againſt the true Religion: Coercive power exerciſed againſt falſe Religion, is no Tyranny, no ſin at all, but an Act of Juſtice, or Religion. Secondly he forgot himſelf in this Aſſertion; and did not remember, that in Rome it ſelf, Italy and Spaine, &amp;c. where that Soul Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny is moſt rigorouſly exerciſed, (ſetting up a falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and perſecuting the true, in their High commiſſion, and Inquiſition Courts:) there is as yet, the greateſt peace and proſperity, and flouriſhing of thoſe Nations, their ſins being not yet mature, for their long ago determined judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. However, it ſeems, thoſe Politician, are not of this mans Cabinet Council, that Toleration of all Religions, is one of the Pillars of a States Settlement: Its experimented too much, and too long, through many ages, that no hatreds (and ſo, no differences,) are like thoſe of different Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and (which is obſervable) the nearer they come unto an union in matters of Religion, (if yet there be ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43574:4"/>the more ſtrong and deadly are their hatreds, the more fierce and violent their Animoſities. The Jew and the Samaritan were; The Proteſtants and Papiſts, The Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran Arminians and Calviniſts &amp;c. are at this day, the moſt deadly enemies. The reaſon is well given, by one not <q>meanly learned, [They both plead for their God; and that man hath no Religion, that can put up an Indignity offered to his God.]</q> See that ſtory Act. 19.23. &amp;c. But Thirdly, he forgot himſelf once more; and did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that all thoſe miſeries (or moſt of them) have fallen upon this Nation, ſince the deſired Liberty of conſcience was gratified with a Toleration, or Connivence at leaſt. And whither they will ever end, till Religion be eſtabliſhed in truth, purity and power, is a probleme not yet determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but may be, ere we have done.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Reaſon why Soul tyranny is ſo heinous a ſin, and cauſe of our miſeries, he gives to be this; that [This <q>Nation hath been deeply gurley of it above theſe hundred years]</q> He means forſooth in proſecuting Papiſts, not for their Religion, but their Rebellion, and rebellious prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What is this, but to call our Church and State Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors? But of this more anon.</p>
            <p>It is true, (which is his third Reaſon of our miſeries) <q>[Each party objects perſecution to another, as the cauſe of all their miſeries]</q> But one party only truly: For, as there is but one true Religion, ſo there can be no perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion properly but of that, the reſt is a juſt proſecution of errors and hereſies, that deſtroy not only the Faith, but the Souls of many. And his diſtinction I deſire may be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,
<note place="margin">Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was one of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged grounds of the late war, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <q>as of uſe hereafter. But that this was the cauſe, [or principle ground of the late wars between King and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament]</q> is is utterly falſe: The ground of their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as they held them forth) was the encroachment upon their civil Liberties, and priviledges of Parliament: but I leave this to them whom it concerns; as for what is made the judgments of others, concerning our miſeries, by Papiſts, Presbyterians, Royaliſts Independents it is not worth the while to debate; Its like every party will remove the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43574:4"/>from it ſelf, and charge it upon others, let them agree it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>He is now drawing towards his main buſineſs; [what ever the ſin be, that hath drawn the foreſaid Judgments upon theſe Nations; it is certain, with allmoſt all Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Unbyaſſed men, that this State eſpecially as matters now ſtand, in ſuch a variety of Religions ſhall never be firmly ſetled, under any form of Government, unleſs it be built upon ſuch a ſolid Foundation, as may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and ſecure the peoples liberties, both Religious and Civil.]</q> leave but out theſe words [eſpecially as matters now ſtand in ſuch a variety of Religion] which have a ſecret deſign, as we ſhall hear preſently; the thing will be granted <q>by all prudent men, [that no State can be firmly ſetled, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be built upon ſuch a ſolid foundation, as may aſſert and ſecure the peoples liberties, both civil and Religious.]</q> But, I pray, what is that foundation? In his Title page he ſpeaks of two ſolid foundations for the ſettlement of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and makes them there and here, to be the peoples civil and Religious Liberties: when as theſe themſelves, do need a foundation to ſecure and ſettle them upon, which he cunningly conceals and is unwilling to diſcover; for <q>thus he aſſerts again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 4.</note> [The two pillars whereupon this State muſt be ſetled, are the Spiritual and civil liberties of the people, that is, in the Parliaments language, as Men, as Chriſtians.]</q> But upon what foundation, ſhall theſe two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſtand? The peoples Liberties civil or Religious, are but the walls, or roof of this building; and as he ſaid before, muſt be built upon ſome other ſolid foundation, which what <q>it is, I deſire to know. He ſeems to reſolveit, into [<hi>juſt Lawes,</hi> to free the people from Slavery in their Perſons, and Oppreſſion in their Goods.]</q> And indeed, that may go for one of the foundations to ſettle a State upon, <hi>(viz) Righteouſnes,</hi> to aſſert and ſecure their Civil and Religious Liberties; but there is another, and a ſtronger foundation, and that is, the <hi>True Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed and practiſed; of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>For the firſt pillar or foundation, that of civil liberties of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43574:5"/>the people, he ſays, he ſhall ſpeak but a little; and I leſs; it is not our main buſineſs in hand: Three things only he <q>delivers concerning the civil Liberties. [1 That they were much more violated ſince the Kings death, then before in his time; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. In their Repreſentatives, when the Major part of the Parliament members were violently thruſt out of the Houſe, and divers of them Impriſoned; and much more when they were diſſolved without any Lawful Authority, by force and power of the ſword, which the peoples ſervants turned againſt themſelves. 2. By the change of Government and Election of a new ſupreme Magiſtrate, without the ſuffrages of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp;c. 3. When freeborn perſons were impriſoned by Arbitrary power, and inhumanly uſed in Priſon; Trepanning men into Plots, and then cruelly executed &amp;c. Laſtly in their Goods, by exorbitant and continual Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes, &amp;c.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then 2. like a good Phyſitian or Stateſman, he preſcribes the Remedies to theſe our Maladies: I ſhall but <q>name them: 1. [That ſome courſe be taken to make the power of the ſword ſubordinate to the civil power; that the Souldiers be not ſuffered any more to domineere over their Maſters: as the Romane Praetorian bands did, and the Turks Janiſaries do. 2. That no perſon be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, nor his goods touched, without breach of a known Law 3. That at length the people may be freed from their long and exorbitant Taxes; by reducing the Army to as ſmall and competent a number as can be, &amp;c. 4. All poſſible means uſed to quicken Trade, &amp;c.]</q> 3. He ſeems to propheſie once more to the little comfort of the people. <q>[When all is done, (let them make the beſt Settlement they can) the people are not like to be in ſo good a caſe, as they were in the Kings time, &amp;c. The Government ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, cannot be maintained without a continued Army, and Navy, nor thoſe, without continual Taxes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and other inſupportable burthens, &amp;c.]</q> which with him, I leave to the conſideration of the Preſent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43574:5"/>
            <p>
               <q>He now comes to the [other maine Baſis or Pillar, that muſt uphold the great Fabrick of this State, to make it ſtand firme and ſure, the Spiritual or Religious Liberties of the people; which conſiſts in this, that no perſon profeſſing Faith in Chriſt, be moleſted or oppreſſed in his conſcience, for his judgment in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or in things relating to the worſhip of God.]</q> 1. That true Religion maintained in its power and purity, is a maine B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſis or Power of a State, I have often heard; but the peoples Religious Liberties, are but the product and fruit of that Religion, or of civil Righteouſnes, in a well ſetled State, 2. If by Religious Liberty, he meane, (as he does) Toleration of all Religions, in all that pretend to conſcience; that every man, may not only think and be on what Religion he pleaſe, but practiſe accordingly, it is to be feared, it will in ſtead of a ſolid foundation, prove a quickſand or quagmire, and quickly ſink, or draw after it the peoples civil Liberties, which is his other pillar: For is there not a conſcience to be made in civil Liberties? And muſt not a man follow his conſcience in civil things as well as in Religious? Suppoſe a man be an Anabaptiſt, that out of conſcience denies all Magiſtracy; or a Leveller, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſt, that hold all things ought to be common, goods and wives and all; may he be ſuffered to follow his Conſcience in theſe things? Or may he be reſtrained or puniſhed, if he take another mans goods, or abuſe his wife? &amp;c. If ſo, is not this to exerciſe a coercive power over Conſcience? If not, will it not deſtroy, as ſome Principles of Religion, ſo all Humane Society? Let him but make the peoples civil Liberties commenſurable, with his Religious Liberties, that is, that as any man may be of any Religion, ſo every man may, in civil affairs, do what ſeems good in his own eyes, without reſtraint upon his Conſcience, and ſee what a Common-wealth he hath Setled, upon the foundations of Civil and Religious Liberties. He may find the patterne of it, in the 5. or 6. laſt Chapters of the Book of Judges.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>But wherein doth this Spiritual Liberty conſiſt? [In this, that no perſon profeſſing faith in Chriſt, be mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43574:6"/>or oppreſſed in his conſcience, for his judgment in matters of Religion &amp;c.]</q> If this be the meaning, that no man ſhall be moleſted in his conſcience, for his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, in matters of Religion, and Worſhip, it will eaſily be granted; for what Magiſtrate, or Church, can take cognizance of mens judgments, while they keep them to themſelves? But the queſtion is, whether every man that profeſſes faith in Chriſt, muſt be left to himſelf, to publiſh and propagate his erroneous and heretical judgment to others; and to practiſe openly, what worſhip he, in his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring judgment, thinks to be true? Beſides conſcience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, (and ſo Religion) is true or falſe; if it be truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the true Religion, he ought not to be moleſted or oppreſſed in conſcience, in matters of Religion: But if falſe; to deny ſome kind of moleſtation (though we allow not opreſſion) to ſuch a conſcience, is to deny charity to a ſoul running headlong to Hell for feare of troubling a miſleading Conſcience: Contrary to that Scripture Rule; [Of ſome have compaſſion,
<note place="margin">Jude v. 22. 23.</note> making a difference, and others ſave with feare, pulling them out of the fire:]</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He makes the Religious Liberty of the people, to conſiſt in this, [That no perſon profeſſing faith in Chriſt, be moleſted in his conſcience &amp;c.] But this Rule is too narrow, and too ſtrait-laced; allowing a coercive power, to moleſt ſome conſciences; <hi>viz.</hi> of ſuch as profeſs not faith in Chriſt; And ſuch an abortive brat, is that late Act of Parliament (falſly ſo called) made in more haſt, than good Speed, (the night before their laſt diſſolution by the Army) for Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of tender conſciences, almoſt in the ſame words. For if no perſon may be moleſted for conſcience, then not a Jew, that denies and blaſphemes Jeſus Chriſt: not a Turke for Mahometan worſhip; not an Heathen, that worſhips the Sun, or ſome old worm-eaten Idol; not any man of any Religion whatever. All or any of theſe may ſet up their Temples, and worſhip of their Gods in England, without any moleſtation of conſcience: For they have conſciences as well as other men; and act according to their conſciences; as well as they, and conſcience (ſays he, ſay all men) may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43574:6"/>not be forced: Behold an Univerſal Toleration indeed. Would he ſee a parallel to it? He may find it (I ſay not, in <hi>New Rome,</hi> where Jews and others find far more favour than proteſtants; but) either in old <hi>Rome,</hi> where they had a Pantheon of all Gods; or in <hi>Solomons</hi> old age and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting times, allowing, (under the view of Gods own Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) high places to all his wives Idols, and a Toleration to <q>worſhip them: 1. King 11.7, 8. [Then did <hi>Solomon</hi> build an high place for <hi>Chemoſh</hi> the abomination of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> in the hill that is before <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and for <hi>Moloch,</hi> the abomination of the children of <hi>Ammon;</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe did he for all his ſtrange wives, which burnt incenſe and ſacrificed to their Gods.]</q> 
               <hi>England</hi> (it ſeems) is grown old, and is come to <hi>Solomons</hi> dotage; an hundred year (or thereabouts, the age of <hi>Solomon</hi>) it is, ſince the firſt Reformation from Popery, by proteſtant Religion, (ſo long this Author accounts this our Religion, to have perſecuted the Papiſts, as above:) and that which ſhe could never be perſwaded to do, in her younger days, (<hi>viz.</hi> to grant a Toleration to Papiſts or other Sectaries) ſhe now in her dotage, in favour to her outlandiſh Paramours, the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, hath by a pretended Parliament, too liberally gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: That which the former Kings and Parliaments, both when Popiſh, and ſince they had the name of Proteſtants, would never yield; that which the King of Scots, would rather looſe the Aſſiſtance offered by two potent Popiſh Princes, to ſettle him in his Throne, than yeild unto: That which Papiſts and Jeſuites deny to yield to Proteſtants, in their dominions, that this lower and latter end of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Parliament, hath yielded to Papiſts, and the worſt of Sectaries; To the ſhame of Parliaments, our Nation, and Religion; But I forbear.</p>
            <p>But to the Setlement, he ſays; [The Government of theſe Nations as the caſe now ſtands, cannot be firmly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, without taking away all Reſtraint over Mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and granting an innocent Toleration.] This is the queſtion now between us. In the ſtating whereof, are theſe things very conſiderable. 1. He qualifies it, with theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43574:7"/>words, [as the caſe now ſtands] which a little after, he explains by theſe words [eſpecially when variety of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions have got footing in a Nation.] 1. It ſeems then, where the caſe is otherwiſe, that variety of Religions have got no footing, it may be lawful to lay ſome Reſtraint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on erring conſciences, and to deny the moſt innocent To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration: But did he not ſay univerſally, no man profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing Chriſt, is to be moleſted in conſcience, for his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of Religion? Which if it were true, no ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes nor exeptions need to be put in; no Reſtraint muſt be laid upon mens conſciences, to ſtart or publiſh ſome new Religion, according to their conſciences; for that will prove a way to unſettle that Nation or Church. 2. Muſt all reſtraint of conſcience be taken away? What, of thoſe conſciences, whoſe principles are deſtructive, not only to Religion in the Church, but alſo to the peace and ſafety of the State; as thoſe of Papiſts, that it is Lawful to murder Kings, made heretical by the Pope; or to follow Impulſes of Spirit, to kill Anti-Chriſtian Prieſts, as the Quakers (the Jeſuites diſciples) now begin to aſſert and avow? That State that will allow ſuch conſciences with ſuch prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, deſerve to be deſtroyed, as having neither Policy, Prudence, nor Piety: Yet all Reſtraint, in this caſe muſt be taken away, ſays our Author, and an innocent tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (which is a kind of contradiction) granted: 3. But ſee the Impudence of Jeſuites: They have been the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to give variety of Religions footing in the Nation; and now, they tell us, as the caſe now ſtands, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot be ſetled, till all reſtraint of conſcience be taken away, and an Innocent toleration granted: But hear his reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>[All men know, the freedome of conſcience in matters of Religion, is the laſt, and higheſt intereſt of man, valued by him above all earthly things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing can be more earneſtly deſired by him: And nothing is more repugnant to man, than a Reſtraint or Coercive Power over his conſcience; and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but raiſe a deep diſcontent in him, and earneſt deſire
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43574:7"/>to be free of that ſoul-tyranny; and to wiſh, and work (if it be in their power) and make a change of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: whence it clearly followes, that that ſtate which puts a reſtraint upon mens conſciences, eſpecially when variety of Religions hath got a footing in it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well and ſolidly ſetled, but is expoſed to unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable troubles,</q> jealouſies, and danger of ruine.] Thus far the Jeſuite; To which we ſay, Liberty of Conſcience, in profeſsion of the true Religion, is a thing of ſpecial va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and by all deſired; but liberty granted to erroneous and heretical conſciences, is a thing moſt dangerous and deſtructive, to their own and other ſouls, and by no wiſe man to be deſired, nor by any religious State to be granted. But obſerve again, thoſe interpoſed words (eſpecially when variety of Religions hath got a footing in a Nation.) And again, (eſpecially as the caſe now ſtands) obſerve, (what was noted above) that it was the deſign of the Jeſuites, on purpoſe, to break our Religion into fractions, that ſo they might plead for toleration of all; upon this ground, that the State cannot now be ſolidly ſetled, if they put a reſtraint upon mens conſciences: At <hi>Rome,</hi> and elſe where, where they are all of one falſe Religion; they may, and do put reſtraint upon mens conſciences, that whatever they think in their judgments, they may not dare to publiſh their opinions, and ſet up new Religions: May not a Proteſtant Magiſtrate, lay a reſtraint upon all Religions, but the true, by way of remedy, which they do by way of prevention, knowing, that if variety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions be ſuffered to get footing in a Nation, they will unſettle the peace of the Nation, as well, as where they have already got footing: But enough of that; In particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to the Argument, I ſay many things. 1. It is no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox to ſay, conſcience it ſelf (though the body may) cannot be forced or reſtrained, (as the will cannot) but is ever ſeen, when the tongue or body may be bound: [The Word of God is not bound,] though I be, ſaid the great Apoſtle in Priſon. The conſcience hath its freedome, either to practiſe according to it, or to ſuffer in its reſtraint, not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43574:8"/>with diſcontent (as he) but upon choice, and joyfully too. 2. That's no good conſcience, that deſires, and works to be free from ſoul-tyranny, by working a change of that Government, by which it is racked. The Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians, (when they had power in their hand, as the greater number) did not ſo, but pleaded and urged, obedience either active or paſſive, to the worſt of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Whence it appears, that this is no part of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jeſus, but a drop of Jeſuitiſme: That reſtraint of conſcience may (lawfully) put men upon deſigns to ruine the State, under which they live and ſuffer. This may be part of the Politicians Catechiſme, which he ſpeaks of, hatched in the <hi>Conclave</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Jeſuites juncto's; but is wiſedome <hi>earthly; ſenſual, diveliſh,</hi> yea, too often practiſed by them, as in other States, ſo in ours of <hi>England;</hi> 
               <q>His own inſtances ſhall convince him, [that of the forraign Inveſion, in the year 88, and again by a deteſtible Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Plot, of ſome few deſperate Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Deteſtible Plots indeed, and deſperate, not by ſome few Papiſts (or as one called them, unfortunate Gentlemen, not for the undertaking, but unfortunate in their ſucceſs) not by ſome few Papiſts, but by an Armado the one, the other not without the Approbation of many Prieſts and Jeſuites, and the Canonization of the chief Contriver, <hi>Garnet,</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> True Proteſtants have ever hated ſuch Religion, as allowes People to rebell againſt, and endeavour the <hi>ruine</hi> or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of the State, rather then ſuffer for Religion: As for thoſe inſtances, in <hi>France, Holland, Scotland,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; I ſhall not take upon me to juſtifie or condemn them, becauſe I know not their grounds; they are old enough, and able to plead for themſelves: But this only I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the conſideration of the preſent Powers; <q>[That though ſome other Sects or ſeveral Religions (as he calls them) have made Inſurrections, ſince the change of the Government (above ten years ſince) to the danger of the State; yet, thoſe that are true Preſbyterians, have never in the leaſt, deviſed any Plots, or moved a Finger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of the Powers that have been uppermoſt, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43574:8"/>have ſat ſtill in ſilence and ſubmiſſion, reſolved to yield active obedience to their commands, where lawfully they may, or paſſive obedience, to ſuffer, where their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences dare not act, or approve.]</q> And to this man, I ſay, The Presbyterians have never exerciſed any Soul tyranny over mens conſciences, upon any of different opinions from them, in matters of Religion, (as never having had any ſuch power granted them) unleſs upon their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Members, in a ſpiritual way, which himſelf allowes. Whom have they ever puniſhed in their bodies, mulcted in their goods, cropt off their ears impriſoned, baniſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They abhor the thoughts, (much more the practiſe) of ſuch ſoul-tyranny, and leave it either to the former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or to his holy Father the Pope, from whence it had its Original. Yet theſe are the men, whom this bold <q>
                  <hi>Calumniator</hi> dare aſperſe [as overturners of the State, (ſome more preciſe ſort of Proteſtants, who paſt all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, under the name of Puritans) and that upon the ſame ſcore of Religion, to be free of all reſtraint of their conſciences, and enjoy a greater freedome.]</q> The Lord rebuke thee, thou ſlanderous Tongue; that reſtraint was laid upon the conſciences of thoſe honeſt men, who were unjuſtly called Puritans, is too evident to be denyed: That they might ſeek to be free from that reſtraint, may alſo be yielded, but not in any ſeditious, or tumultuous way; but in a way of Addreſs to the Supream Power of Parliament, abhorring the very thought of overturning the State; though by the fraud and ſubtilty of ſome, that have followed, which they never intended: Himſelf hath told us, what was one, (and a chief, if not the only) cauſe <q>of the late Wars, [Arbitrary Government, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching upon the Peoples Civil Liberties.</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 5.] not at all or not primarily, <hi>[upon the ſcore of Religion]</hi> though they might juſtly fear, that by Arbitrary Government, Religion at laſt might come to ſuffer; as all that know the ſtate of thoſe times, cannot but confeſs. 3. As for his <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>toleration,</hi> let us hear what he ſayes; [An inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Toleration in matters of Religion ſecures all, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43574:9"/>cements the Peoples greateſt Intereſt, to preſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Common-wealth; whereof we ſee a near and clear example in the Common-wealth of <hi>Holland.</hi>]</q> But 1. Why may he not conclude the like for Peoples civil Liberties? An innocent, and inoffenſive <hi>community</hi> of all things, will ſecure all, and cement the Peoples Intereſt, to preſerve and defend the Common wealth, wherein they enjoy ſuch freedome: It is <hi>propriety</hi> that puts wicked men upon Breach of Peace; that puts men upon ſtealing one from another: Let rich men but be perſwaded, to let their houſes, goods, and money be free, and common to all, there will be no diſturbance in the State; ſo in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion; let men have liberty to be of any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or none, true, or falſe; let them blaſpheme the Name of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, worſhip them with what worſhip they pleaſe, though forbidden; and the Church and States need not trouble themſelves, or ſear any troubles. It is the Magiſtrate, or the Church, that by denying People this liberty, and laying reſtraint upon their conſciences, that are guilty of all unſetling diſturbances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. The To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of the Hollander: I never yet heard a truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious man to commend or approve, till now, if now it is, I fear, more out of policy, than piety: But I believe, if the Hollander had not a better Guard by Sea and Land to ſecure and defend his State, than the cement, or untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Mortar of Toleration; he had long ere this been reduced, either to his old Maſter, or to utter deſtruction: However, <hi>malè parta, male dilabentur,</hi> when the time comes: We ſee the fruit of Toleration in <hi>England,</hi> ſince it hath been granted; the variety of Religions, as it hath ſerved in one ſenſe, to ſtrengthen a prevailing party, by the politick Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera:</hi> So it hath made no ſmall diſturbances in the Church and State; and had they not an Army to quiet them, had long ere this, laid them in the duſt, and the Nation in aſhes: And what will be the iſſue, God only knows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His next Reaſon, or Argument, is borrowed from one Mr. <hi>Collier,</hi> an Anabaptiſt at leaſt, if not Jeſuited, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43574:9"/>conſiſts of many, no leſs than ſour Arguments, which all <q>have reſpect to the Magiſtrate, [As by Coercive power in matters of Religion, becoming guilty of high Treaſon, againſt Jeſus Chriſt, in uſurping upon his prerogative:]</q> But the man hath quite miſtaken the queſtion, (as no doubt this Author knows, but would take no notice of it.) This <q>he undertakes to prove, [That it is unlawful for the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to pretend any right of Coercive power, over mens conſciences, and an heinous ſin in him to exerciſe it.]</q> The thing is true in it ſelf, but not to the queſtion. The Magiſtrate hath no more Coercive power over mens conſciences, than the Church hath over mens bodies: Chriſt only is Lord over the conſcience: Magiſtrates cannot impoſe any Laws of their own over the conſciences of men, nor force any to believe or practiſe, contrary to the Laws of Chriſt, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their conſciences; or puniſh them for not ſo believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. But the queſtion is, whether a Magiſtrate Chriſtian, at leaſt, profeſſing the true Religion, may not uſe his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to command profeſſed Chriſtians, to the obſervance of the Laws of Chriſt, and the outward preſcribed worſhip of God, and puniſh them for not conforming thereunto? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo, he may not reſtrain men from publiſhing and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctſing of Errors and Hereſies, and falſe worſhip, contrary to the true Religion, to the perverting and deſtroying of mens ſouls? And if his Arguments prove not the Negative of theſe, they prove nothing. But let us hear them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>[The Magiſtrate hath received no ſuch power, from Chriſt in the New Teſtament, in matters relating to Faith and Worſhip: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Chriſt hath reſerved the power over conſcience to himſelf, as Lord of it.]</q> The whole of this may be granted, and is granted above, in a right ſence, without any prejudice to the queſtion between us: Chriſt only is Lord over the Conſcience, to preſcribe Laws of Faith, and Worſhip: 2. The ſecond is the ſame with the firſt in fenſe. The Magiſtrate cannot impoſe Rules of Faith and Worſhip upon people, &amp;c. But may he not impoſe the Laws of God and Chriſt upon his people? And ought he not therein to be obeyed? And Puniſh thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43574:10"/>them, or walk contrary to them? And if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand contrary to thoſe Rules of Chriſt, though he muſt not be therein obeyed, muſt he not Paſſively be ſubmitted to? And what if Chriſt have not in the New Teſtament committed ſuch power to the Magiſtrate, (as will be proved he hath) is it not ſufficient that he hath committed it to him in the old Teſtament. And that not only the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> but Heathen Kings have executed ſuch a Power? See <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29. and 6.26. So that it is a Moral duty of a Magiſtrate, known by the light of Nature, as Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, to publiſh the Laws of God, to command obedience to them, and to puniſh Trangreſſors: and is not this a Coercive power committed to the Magiſtrate? 3. He <q>thus argues; [If the Magiſtrates have ſuch a power, then all or ſome: If all, then Heathen Magiſtrates have it, but that's abſurde: If Chriſtian only, they may be of divers Religions, and command contrary to Chriſts Rules, one, one Religion, another, another, &amp;c.]</q> This is the ſum of his Dilemmatical diſcourſe. But the Anſwer is eaſie; this power (we ſpeak of) belongs to all Magiſtrates, as Magiſtrates, (even Heathens as afore) though all are not in a capacity, or have ability to perform it. As in the fifth Commandment, all parents are bound to inſtruct, and command their children to know and fear God, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their diſobedience; but Heathen parents cannot right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do it: The power of the Magiſtrate (who is <hi>pater patriae</hi>) is the very ſame, in a greater latitude, and belongs; to the ſame Commandment: though all cannot perform it, but <q>that's their fault. <hi>Obj.</hi> [They may be of different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions or beliefs, and think themſelves in the right, and ſo every one that hath power, will perſecute another; Proteſtants, Papiſts, and <hi>contra.</hi>]</q> At their perill be it, if they believe falſly, and perſecute the true Religion: But ought they to do ſo? May they that are of a falſe Religion perſecute thoſe that profeſs the true Religion? Did he not ſay, above, this was the <hi>moſt heinous ſin?</hi> And may not they that profeſs and have the true Religion, proſecute thoſe that are heretical, to bring them to a true belief and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43574:10"/>This caſe is parallel: A Magiſtrate may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh offenders againſt righteouſneſs in civil affairs, <hi>Ergo,</hi> He or another may perſecute others for righteouſneſs; but <q>(ſayes he) [Allow this, that divers Religions may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute one another, and what confuſion will this bring into a State, into the World?]</q> 
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Is there no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between proſecution of evil doers? and perſecution of the innocent, every Thief, and every Heretick, if pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or reſtrained, cry out of perſecution. But how unjuſtly? 2. Hath not Chriſt foretold it, and by his Providence ſo orders it, that there ſhall be perſecution of the good for his ſake, and for righteouſneſs ſake? yea, and command his people to ſuffer it (not with oppoſition, or a deſire to ruine and ſubvert that State that offers it) but without impatience, with greateſt joy and gladneſs. How unlike to Jeſus, are our Jeſuites? 4. His fourth Argument <q>is this; [Chriſt hath committed his authority in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, relating to worſhip, to his Church; and commands to tell the Church, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Not to the Magiſtrate.]</q> But 1. Why did he leave out in matters of Faith, that might have given us cauſe to ſuſpect the Jeſuite, who allowes to his Pope, power in matters of Faith, in his <hi>Trent</hi> Creed; but in worſhip, the Church (he would have us believe) have ſome latitude of power, which ſhe hath not, except in meer circumſtances, not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the worſhip it ſelf. 2. For I ask, Hath Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his Authority to the Church, to coin new Articles of Faith, and new forms of Worſhip? If not, the Church and Magiſtrate are herein equal in their power; between whom this Argument would inſinuate a difference. The Church hath no Authority Coercive upon mens conſciences, in matters relating to Faith and Worſhip, more then the Mageſtrate hath; but both are, in their own way, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and look to the execution of Chriſts rules in both: The only difference is, that the power of the Church is Spiritual, that of the Magiſtrate Corporal. And they may not meddle with each other Powers; the Magiſtrate may no more exerciſe the ſpiritual power of the Church, than the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43574:11"/>Church may exerciſe power over mens bodies or eſtates. 3. This Diſputer, (if he underſtand what he ſayes) would inſinuate, that Chriſt hath committed Authority over mens conſciences, to the Church, which the Apoſtle earneſtly diſclaims, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. And yet the Church hath ſome kind of Coercive power over her Members, as appears in her cenſure of Excommunication; which our Author ſayes, is a worſe puniſhment, than all the Magiſtrate can inflict <q>upon the body; [as giving men over to the World, and to Satan.] Now look back a little, and ſum up all. It is a general rule, laid down by all ſides; [Conſcience may not, muſt not be forced in matters of Religion, by any Coercive power:]</q> Then, neither by the Church, nor Magiſtrate, neither ſpiritually nor corporally: The Church may no more force conſcience, than the Magiſtrate; yet the Church exerciſing and executing Examination upon an Heretick, or ſcandalous perſon, exerciſes a Coerſive power; and (as they will ſay) over their conſciences; for they verily believe themſelves in the right Religion: Therefore, either the exerciſe of Coercive power by the Church, is alſo unlawful, and ſo he hath deſtroyed the power of the Church in matters of Religion, as well as of the Magiſtrate, or elſe, it is no force over mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, but over the errors of their conſciences. And laftly, If it be lawful for the Church to reſtrain and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftiſe an Heretick by her ſpiritual cenſures, without any force to her conſcience; Why may it not be lawful for the Magiſtrate to reſtrain ſuch a ſoul deſtroying Heretick, by bodily puniſhments, and yet without force upon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Why may not the Magiſtrate deliver ſuch a man to the Jaylor, as the Church delivers him to the Devil? Eſpecially, the end of both being, (as much as in them lies) to ſave his ſoul: Whence I conclude againſt him; this Power of the Magiſtrate, is no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> of the Dominion of Chriſt, or the Power of the Church; much lefs, <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt Chriſt: Thus weakly hath M. <hi>Collier</hi> argued hitherto; we ſhall hear of him again are long.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43574:11"/>3. His third Reaſon is borrowed from as wiſe an Author, <q>[The Vindicatour of Sir <hi>Henry Vane.</hi> [Nothing can be more againſt the ſpiritual good of People, than to make them hypocrites in Religion, profeſſing to believe what they do not] Learned Soul!</q> Hath not the State and Church of <hi>England</hi> commanded all their People to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent our Congregations, under a penalty, every Lords Day? Hath not this man accordingly frequented them? And hath he been all this while an hypocrite, profeſſing to believe, what he doth not? But if force in Religion make men hypocrites, why did God commend <hi>Abraham</hi> to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe all the males of his family? Why did the Godly Magiſtrates command all their Subjects, under the Old Teſtament, to ſerve the Lord, according to the worſhip preſcribed? Did God or men intend to make them hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites? Which they muſt have done, if Coercive power did make them ſo: Alas, moſt men are hypocrites alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, though they be not forced to worſhip God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Coercive power does not make, but find, and diſcovers hypocrites: Muſt not God be obeyed, though men be hypocrites? But real Chriſtians, (who only can truly be forced againſt conſcience) do not turn hypocrites, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe obedience, and chuſe to ſuffer, which diſcovers their faith and patience, and bring much glory to God. There muſt be perſecution (as well as Hereſies) that they which are approved may be known, It is therefore by accident, that ſuch force makes men appear hypocrites, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to obey the Laws of God; the Law of God irritates corruption, but cauſes it not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13, 23. If then God, or men from God, command men to worſhip God; according to his will, they find many hypocrites, but do not make them ſuch: They ſin, if they ſerve him not; and if hypocritically, they ſin alſo; and its hard to ſay, which is worſt: But this is ſome of the new light of this age; that Children muſt not be taught their Commandments, Creed, or Lords Prayer, or to read the Scriptures, becauſe they are yet hypocrites; or none muſt receive the Lords Supper, that knows not himſelf regenerate, leſt it make him an hypocrite. Enough of this.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:43574:12"/>4. His fourth Reaſon is taken out of the Levellers Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm. A Levelling Principle indeed, to deny the Magiſtrates power in matters of Religion firſt, and then in civil affairs: If all were levelled, and but content to be ſo, what need, what uſe of a Magiſtrate? But hear their worthy Reaſon: <q>[It's againſt the nature of faith and worſhip to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: Chriſt hath ordained the preaching of the Goſpel, to be the outward means of converting ſouls, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Ordinances for puniſhment of erroneous and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> This hath been ſpoken to in anſwering Mr. <hi>Colliers</hi> firſt and ſecond reaſons, and in the laſt before: But I add further, it contradicts it ſelf twice: 1. In ſaying, that the preaching of the word is the outward means of Converſion; and yet denies any force to bring profeſſed Chriſtians to the attending on that means. 2. That they allow ſpiritual puniſhment, which is a greater force, for reducing erroneous and heretical perſons; and yet denies not only the Magiſtrate, to uſe any the leaſt force to the bodies or eſtates of men, but any force at all over mens conſciences: If no force may be uſed, then not the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, as was ſaid afore. Laſtly, he takes for granted (what we utterly deny) that we allow the Church a power, to puniſh miſ-believers (or miſ-livers) in bodies or purſes. Some have done ſo, but I hope they have had time to repent it, for ſo diſhonouring the Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The next is from a better Author, but to as little <q>purpoſe [From the parable of the Tares among the Wheat, both muſt be let alone till the Harveſt; the Wheat are the elect, the Tares are Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> It might be enough to anſwer this, that it is a parable, which is a ſimilitude, and muſt not be ſtrained beyond its ſcope, which is, to let us know, that good and bad, upright and hypocrites muſt be in the Church, till the end of the World: And yet ſome are about to make a Church of all Saints, and to pluck up the Wheat, in pretence of pulling up the Tares: But 2. By Tares, cannot well be meant heretical perſons (not in <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s judgment) for he and other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, with the Scripture, allow Excommunication of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43574:12"/>and ſcandalous perſons, which is not only a pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Tares, but a caſting them out of the Church, into Hell, without repentance. 3. Our Saviour himſeif tells us, who are the tares, the children of the wicked one, and ſuch as do iniquity. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.38.41. Now hence it would follow, that neither Church, nor Magiſtrate muſt puniſh ſuch, but let them alone to the end of the World; a pleaſiing Doctrine to thieves, and all wicked perſons. But if, notwithſtanding this parable, it be lawful for the Church, to puniſh Hereticks ſpiritually, and for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to puniſh them corporally; he hath miſtaken the parable: And if the Magiſtrate may puniſh a murdour bodily, for killing the bodies of men; why ſhould it be unlawful for him to puniſh an heretical ſeducer, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes mens ſouls, and that eternally? I leave him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <q>6. He fetches this next Reaſon from far [from the judgment of the ancients, and practiſe of the primitive Church; <hi>Lactan. Tertull.</hi> &amp;c. who ſeem to deny all force in Religion:]</q> A little may ſerve for this. There is a difference to be put between Heathens and Chriſtians, in matters of Religion: The Ancients ſpeak againſt forcing Heathens into Chriſtianity, till they firſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and convinced of the truth thereof, not of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling profeſſed Chriſtians, to the outward Worſhip of God, as the King of <hi>Judah</hi> did. 2. The practiſe of Chriſtian Emperours, was accordingly, for the moſt part, with reſpect to Heathens. Yet ſome of them made Edicts, to command all their ſubject to be of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and others, as were eaſie to inſtance. 3. In Preſsing this ARgument too far, he forgot himſelf, that he makes his Pope, and Popiſh Princes worſe then Turks, and Furies, in their perſecution of Proteſtants. And let them but give this liberty of conſcience to all their ſubjects, which he pleads for in <hi>England,</hi> and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide their coercive power, and I believe Popery will have but a few clients; moſt of them would quickly forſake their Church and Religion, eſpecially, if they might have the truth freely taught by ſome Proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43574:13"/>7. But a reaſon fatcht from a principle of nature, and <q>natural light, will convince any reaſonable man: [It's againſt the golden rule of natural righteouſneſs; do as we would be done by; and do not to others, what we would not have done to our ſelves; but who would be content to be perſecuted by others for his Religion? &amp;c.]</q> Truly, no man would, or at leaſt ſhould be perſecuted for his true Religion; but he that would not be proſecuted for a falſe Religion, argues himſelf to be unrighteous, and to violate that principle of nature; and another like it, <hi>Aequo animo paenam, qui meruere luant.</hi> Let him make this rule univerſal, and thieves, and malefactors will give him many thanks: What Thieves would be content to be hang'd by a Magiſtrate? <hi>Ergo,</hi> If he get to be a Magiſtrate, he muſt not hang a Thief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Bring it neerer to himſelf, what Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite would be content to be executed, for ſedition, and ſeducement of Proteſtants, from their Religion, and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, <hi>Ergo.</hi> nor ſhould they perſecute Proteſtants in their Dominions: How likes he this? The Golden Rule, is made for true rectifyed conſciences, not for every one that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it: What in true reaſon, I would have another do, or not do, to me; that I ſhould be content to do, or not do to another: If a man ſhould argue thus; I would not be content to be perſecuted for the true Religion, <hi>Ergo,</hi> I muſt not proſecute one that is in the falſe: Or thus, If I am an Heretick, perverting Souls, and would not be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or puniſhed for ſo doing; <hi>Ergo,</hi> I muſt let others alone, and not puniſh them for the ſame; both theſe conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are falſe and unreaſonable, and meer pervertings and crooknings of that Golden Rule: This is a Jeſuitical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; I would not be puniſhed for my ſeduce ment in <hi>England; Ergo,</hi> I may plead for Toleration of Popery, and all Religions: This conſequence, I ſay, is good now in <hi>England,</hi> to cheat ſimple ſouls; but would be denyed with an Inquiſition at <hi>Rome</hi> or in <hi>Spain.</hi> Such another fallacy is that; which followes, a Chriſtian muſt pray for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; <hi>Ergo,</hi> he muſt not perſecute his brother, be he never ſo wicked. <hi>(q. d.)</hi> I muſt pray for a Thief or Murderer,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43574:13"/>Heretick; <hi>Ergo,</hi> I may not proſecute them to juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, corporally the one, ſpiritually the other.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The next reaſon comes yet neerer home; <hi>ad hominem,</hi> as we ſay; and that is thus. [It is againſt our own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples] and the teſtimony of an Adverſary is moſt ſtrong againſt himſelf: Wherein? In three things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <q>1. [We profeſs our ſelves to be fallible, in judging univerſally in matters of Religion, and object it to the Papiſts, pretending infallibility; but by perſecuting others for conſcience, we make our ſelves infallible, as Mr. <hi>Collier</hi> wiely obſerves.]</q> For this, he hath been told; we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute no man for his conſcience, but may proſecute a man for an erring conſcience; which he ſtill concludes, a juſt proſecution, with an unjuſt perſecution. 2. We profeſs our ſelves to be fallible, or not infallible, in the Popiſh ſenſe: He deludes us, with the equivocation of the words. If he mean that we hold our ſelves fallible, <hi>univerſally</hi> in all matters of Religion, that we are uncertain of all points of Religion, and certain of nothing, that were to make us meer <hi>Scepticks</hi> in our Religion, and we own not ſuch a fallibility: On the other ſide, we do not think our ſelves infallible uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally in matters of Religion, as the <hi>Pope does;</hi> but that in ſome fundamental truths, we are infallible, that is, moſt certain of the truths of our Religion, clearly revealed in Scripture, which is an infallible rule; though we are not alwayes able to apply it. But the <hi>Pope</hi> as he makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf infallible in all points of Religion, which he determines out of the <hi>Pontifical Chair;</hi> ſo he does it, in things beſides, and againſt the Scripture; and this we object to him, as an hainous <hi>crime,</hi> and high <hi>uſurpation</hi> of the prerogative of Jeſus Chriſt, ſpeaking in the Scripture. 3. What need is there that we muſt be infallible, to judg and puniſh an <q>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick? why this [We cannot rationally perſecute any man for his conſcience, unleſswe we do not only know that he is in an ertor, but alſo be infallibly ſure, that we are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to an undoubted truth:]</q> Be it ſo, then we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume; we may know that the man is in an errour, (if we may know the truth) and be infallibly ſure, we are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to an undoubted truth; <hi>Ergo,</hi> we may perſecute
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43574:14"/>(we ſay, proſecute) him for his erring conſcience: <hi>e. g.</hi> We know certainly, that he that denies a God, or Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God, and Saviour of the World, is in an error, and we are infallibly ſure, we are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to an undoubted truth, to profeſs a God, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: and <hi>Ergo,</hi> we may, by his own <hi>premiſes,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, or rather proſecute him for his erring conſcience. <q>Whereupon the following aſſertion is moſt unchriſtian and uncharitable: [It would be better for us, to let him alone in his (known, damning) errors, than to force him to ours, which we, (not falſly as he) truly eſteem truth.]</q> [The very mercies of the wicked are cruel:] 4. Theſe men ſeem to be <hi>Scepticks</hi> in their Religion; for if there be any Religion, or rules of faith and worſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in Scripture, we may come to be infallibly ſure, that this is the Truth of God, and thereby diſcover errors, and conſequently may proſecute them, though we be not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally infallible. The Magiſtrates of the Old Teſtament might not force any mans conſcience, more than now; nor were more infallible, than ours are now; yet having a cleer rule of Religion, and worſhip given them; they compelled their ſubjects to obſerve it; why may not ours do ſo now, having a cleer light, and greater illumination? Is it not a certain and infallible truth, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God, and only Saviour of the World? If not, what an uncertain thing is Chriſtianity, which depends upon that one principle? If it be, ſhall any man profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Chriſtian Religion, be ſuffered to deny that truth, and blaſpheme that holy name with impurity, becauſe the Magiſtrate, or Church, is not in all things infallible? Laſtly, as to this firſt principle, <hi>ex ungue leonem;</hi> we may deſcry and diſcover (the Fox) the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> by his ſtrong plea for Toleration to his <hi>Recuſants,</hi> or Papiſts. Though he ſpeak in the perſon of Proteſtants, as if one of them; yet his ſecret, or open girding at the State, ſhews what he is; <q>[Who having laid aſide the King, by whom, and for whom, thoſe laws (of reſtraint) were made, which is indeed the aboliſhing of thoſe Laws; yet we keep up the penalties of thoſe Laws, in vigour againſt Recuſants,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43574:14"/>which ſeems to be a very irrational Act:]</q> And puts this Jeer upon the preſent powers, <q>(by way of thanks or ſcorne) for their granted ſoleration, [That as we have not one particular poſitive <hi>Religion</hi> ſetled, for undoubted truth amongſt us: So we purpoſe not any one <hi>Religion</hi> to the Recuſants, to be followed by them, but at moſt hold them out a medly of all Sects profeſt in the Nation, &amp;c.]</q> 
               <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos, de Seditione querentes?</hi> The Subtle curſed Jeſuites, ſelf condemned men, have broken our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> into ſo many Sects and Fractions, to keep us from Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the true <hi>Religion,</hi> and then make themſelves merry with our diviſions. The Lord rebuke them. This to our firſt principle.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>The next is: [We have always pretended a general Toleration for all tender conſciences, of which kind, there are ſome amongſt the Prelatical and Popiſh party:]</q> And yet they only are excepted from Toleration by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for ſo he means it. <q>But he goes on ſtill, [Grant it to a poor ſneaking fooliſh fellow, that can ſcarce ſpeak ſenſe, and hath hardly a groat in his purſe, to loſe for his conſcience, and deny it to men of Honour, Prudence and Eſtates, ſuffering meerly for their conſcience, as having no tender conſciences.] 1. Me thinks I hear the proud Phariſees ſpeak, in this Jeſuite, [This people that knoweth not the Law is curſed;</q> and Lord I thank thee, I am not as other men:] He cals mean ſimple Chriſtians, <hi>Sneaking Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi> as if they had no conſcience, <q>becauſe they have no Eſtates; He may remember, [Not many Wife, not many Noble or Mighty.]</q> were called, or honoured to be <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Martyrs;</hi> to ſuffer meerly for conſcience: They had too much to loſe, to dare to profeſs Chriſtianity; [But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe, &amp;c.] He may read the reſt, 1 Cor. 1.26 &amp;c. And he makes men of <hi>Honour, Prudence</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> to have tender conſciences, meerly for ſuffering in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: whereas he knows many ſuch may and do ſuffer on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the <hi>Religion</hi> delivered them by Tradition from their Fathers, or out of ſome carnal reſpects: If a man deſired to be looſe and profane, he need not chuſe an eaſier <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43574:15"/>than Popery: And the Divel hath had his <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> as well as Chriſt: <hi>Martyres Satanicae vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian:</hi> &amp;c 2. But I have, I confeſs, often wondered, that thoſe in power, who pretend ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to all tender conſciences, ſhould ſo often, by name, except the Prelatical and Popiſh party; when as, there may be as tender conſciences in ſome of them as in ſome, whom they tolerate; and alſo, their laxe and looſe principles, and theſe reaſons carry toleration for all, or none.</p>
            <p>Some Satisfaction I received from one, that alſo pleads for Toleration, (as I thought) for all <hi>Religions,</hi> (for his Arguments are as ſtrong for all, as for any) why the Popiſh party ſhould not have any Toleration granted them, above all the reſt. Let him be heard ſpeak in his own words. <q>[As for Popery and Idolatry,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>J. Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on.</hi> tract. of civil power, in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cauſes. <hi>p</hi> 35.</note> why they alſo may not plead to be tolerated, I have much leſs to ſay: Their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> the more conſidered, the leſs can it be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a <hi>Religion;</hi> but a <hi>Roman</hi> principallity, rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to keep up her old univerſal Dominion, under a new name and meer ſhadow of a Catholick <hi>Religion;</hi> being indeed more rightly named, a Catholick hereſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scripture, and except in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſupported mainly by a civil and forrain power; juſtly therefore to be ſuſpected, not tolerated by the Magiſtrate of another Country. Beſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, of an Implicite Faith which they profeſs, the conſcience alſo becomes implicit, and ſo by voluntary ſervitude to mans law, forfeits her Chriſtian Liberty. Who then can plead for ſuch a conſcience, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inthraled implicitly to man, inſtead of God, almoſt becomes no conſcience, as the will, not free, becomes no will. Laſtly, for Idolatry, (whereof the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, is juſtly charged, to be deeply guilty) who know; it not to be evidently againſt all Scripture, both of the Old and New Teſtament. And therefore a true Herefie, or rather Impiety; wherein a right conſcience can have nought to do, and the works thereof ſo manifeſt, that a Magiſtrate can hardly err, in prohibiting, and quite removing at leaſt the publick and ſcandalous uſe thereof.]</q> How this will pleaſe Jeſuits, or how they will anſwer it, I he ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43574:15"/>know, nor care: But I ſatisfied my ſelf, with one or both of theſe conſiderations. 1. That they might except them, not out of conſcience, but out of ſtate pollicy; becauſe, on the one ſide; if the prelatical party ſhould have a Tole ration, they might in time return to challenge and take from them, thoſe fat and ſweet morſels of the Biſhops Revenues, which ſome of them have ſwallowed down, and would be loath to vomit up again. On the other ſide, if the Popiſh party ſhould be tolerated (I will not ſay, they ſhould loſe a good Revenue from Sequeſtration of two parts of their Eſtates, though ſome give this for a reaſon) their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are deſtructive to Heretical Magiſtrates, as the Pope can eaſily make them, and ſo ſubverſive of their New Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: Thats one. 2. The other conſideration to ſtay my wonder, was, That, that exception was ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inſerted, by ſome Jeſuitical finger, that if ever that party got power into their hands, they might the more colourable deny Toleration to thoſe, who being in place, did firſt deny it to them: for this is a maxime amongſt the <q>Sectaries [They that deny toleration to others tender conſciences,
<note place="margin">I Milt. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</note> deſerve not to have it for themſelves]</q> And then they that now plead for Toleration of the worſt ſort of tender conſciences, will at laſt, grant more to thoſe, whoſe conſciences are truly tender, and moſt rightly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled: I wiſh I may be a falſe prophet, in this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But hear the next.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>[It is againſt another Principle of ours; we allow people the Bible in the vulgar language, and preſs them to ſearch the Scripture, to find out the mind of God, and at laſt by our coerſive power, will have them believe, as the the Church believes; we bid men (as wiſely Mr <hi>Collier</hi> ſpeaks) ſee with their own eyes, and yet put them to ſee with others eyes.]</q> We bid men (with our Saviour) to ſearch the Scriptures, and with the <hi>Bereans,</hi> not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to believe as the Church believes, (that was the Colliers, and the Papiſts beliefe) but to try the truths held out by Church or Magiſtrate; which if they do faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſincerely, they will ſee the truths with their own <q>eyes: [If any man, will do his will, he ſhall know of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43574:16"/>Doctrine whether it be of God, or whether I ſpeak of my ſelf, <hi>Jo</hi> 7.17.]</q> And we ſuppoſe and take for granted, (which this man makes doubtful) that there is a pattern of ſound words, the true fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and worſhip of God, held forth fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in the Scriptures, and then by the Church or Magiſtrate; and thereupon exhort men, not to take any thing upon truſt of men, which is not faith, but ignorance, or Popiſh credulity; but in matters of Salvation, to ſearch and ſee by their own eyes. And if it happen that private perſons miſtake error for truth, they muſt either be meekly willing to hearken to inſtruction, (which is a ſign of a good conſcience) or reſolve rather to ſuffer for their judgment, than to diſturb the peace of the Church or State: For while they keep it to themſelves, none can take notice of it, or judg them for it. But this diſpute allowes them, either to reſiſt the coercive power, and labour their ſubverſion (as in his firſt Argument) or elſe to be tolerated, though never ſo damnably he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, and practically deſtructive to themſelves or others. True chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Proteſtants, bids thoſe that have the charge of their ſouls (which both Miniſters and Magiſtrates have, in their own way.) Firſt, with meekneſs, and much patience to inſtruct them, and if they ſtill continue obſtinate, like mad men to miſchief themſelves and others, to lay ſetters of reſtraint upon them, either ſpiritual or corporal, that they may do no further hurt.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <q>9. The next Reaſon is this: [It was againſt the judgment of King <hi>James,</hi> and other Kings, and againſt the peoples frequent peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for toleration, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>] Firſt, for King <hi>James,</hi> two of his ſayings are produced; [That God never plants a Church, by violence and bloodſhed.]</q> True, for he left that for the Jeſuites amongſt the poor Indians: So ſpake <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Lantanc.</hi> above; Religion is not to be forced upon Heathens; God does not fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt plant a Church by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, much leſs by bloodſhed; but when a Church is planted (as a Vine) he allows pruning and purging of it, by ſpiritual cenſures; which (in this mans ſenſe) is a kind of force upon conſcience: And the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate being a guardian, or nurſe-keeper of the Church, as Gods vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, is to publiſh and maintain Religion, in the puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of it, which cannot be done without coercive power, not upon mens conſciences, but <q>upon their bodies or eſtates. His other ſpeech, [That he never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any perſecution any againſt the Papiſts, for conſcience ſake, but deſired to be ſecured for civil obedience, which they cannot deny.]</q> Not to tell him that King <hi>James</hi> did not own, but oppoſe their Religion <q>as falſe,</q> [whoſe Faith is Faction, whoſe Religion is Rebellion:] he knows who ſaid it: If he did reſtrain them from practiſing it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, it was not perſecution of them for conſcience ſake, but proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of an erring conſcience: But I ſay, when they were reſtrained from exerciſe of their Religſon, it was with reſpect to a principle of their Religion, denying to give him ſecurity in civil obedience; from <q>a ſtated-deſtroying opinion and practiſe of theirs, [That it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yea, neceſſary, if the Pope command it, to murder and kill here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Kings;]</q> Whereof his predeceſſors and himſelf, had frequent experience, in ſuch like attempts; the examples of other Kings in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating other Keligions, I fear, is rather out of political Intereſt, than <q>real piety: As for that ſcandal upyn the powers, [That the State in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43574:16"/>perſecuting them now, will be greater perſecutors then the old Magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and Biſhops were, yea, than the Spaniſh Inquiſition it ſelf:]</q> I leave to them to anſwer, or chaſtiſe ſuch Jeſuitical inſolence. One thing aſperſive upon the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhops and others, is fouly, and fooliſhly affe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted, <q>and eaſily wiped away. [They to prove the lawfulneſs of their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, againſt the Puritans, derived their orders from <hi>Rome;</hi> yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred with the State to make the Laws, that any that received orders from <hi>Rome,</hi> were Traitors, which was moſt ridiculous.]</q> But 1. The Puritans did not brand their vocation from <hi>Rome;</hi> in the firſt Proteſtant Biſhops in <hi>England;</hi> ſome of them were ordained Presbyters by ſuch; the Browninſts and Anabaptiſts did that. 2. The Biſhops with the State, made a Law, that none of their Miniſters ſhould take orders from <hi>Rome,</hi> in a State way; firſt, becauſe that was a denial of our miniſtry to be good at home. Secondly, it was an owning of the Popes ſupremacy ſpiritual, in <hi>England;</hi> which appears by this, that they ſo far allowed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by a Romiſh Biſhop, that they did not re-ordain thoſe Prieſts, which were converted unto the Proteſtant Religion. But if Papiſts and Jeſuites be of the ſame opinions as afore: That heretical Magiſtrates may be murdered, and maintain revelations, and impulſies of ſpirit, to kill any, whom their ſpirit bids them kill, (which our young Quakers have learnt of them) as the State or Government, what ever it be, (though Kings be gone) have no reaſon in policy to tolerate ſuch; ſo it will be no perſecution of them for conſcience ſake, but a wiſe and juſt proſecution of them, for ſuch deſtructive principles, as make the owners of them unfit to live amongſt men, in any civil ſociety. And as for the petitions of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for liberty of conſcience; as they were made tendered by ſome few Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, whoſe looſe opinions and practiſes will abide no government, not by the generality of the moſt and beſt people of the Land; ſo in a <q>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, it is grated by theſe, [That a care be had of truly tender conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>viz.</hi> [Who profeſs faith in Chriſt, and live peaceably, in godlineſs and honeſty;]</q> But they only deſire ſome diſcipline may be exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch, us either deny Jeſus Chriſt, directly, or by neceſſary conſequence, or live not peaceably, but by earneſt propagation of their errors and he reſies, deſtroy both their own and others ſouls, and diſturb the peace of Church and State; or have neither godlineſs nor holineſs in their lives. Yet theſe that plead for ſuch a Government, are the men againſt whom he <q>cunningly inveighs <hi>p.</hi> 25. [As dangerous perſons, that deſire to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer and tyrannize over other mens conſciences; and as their judgments are not greatly to be heeded, ſo themſelves are rather cloſly to be looked too, leſt they ſet all on fire again], as the Jeſuites have lately done, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cendiaries of all States, when ever they come: And again, he ſtirs up the Nation againſt them <hi>p</hi> 30.</q> [It were juſt, that ſuch boutefeues.]</p>
            <p n="10">
               <q>10. Laſtly, (ſayes he) [coercive power is againſt our own Intereſt at home, and the Proteſtant Intereſt abroad; at home, becauſe by fit, we ſay a foundation of perſecution to our ſelves and poſterity. If it be lawful for us to perſecute others; ſo it will be for them, towards us if they get power: So M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Collier</hi>]</q> According to the proverb, like to like, quoth the Divel to the Collier; for what a fine new way have theſe men found, to fruſtrate the predictions of Chriſt, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> [In the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43574:17"/>
               <q>ſhall have tribulation, <hi>Job.</hi> 16. laſt. All that will live Godly, ſhall ſuffer perſecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Their beſt Intereſt were to ſit ſtill, and meddle with no bodies ſins or errors: How fooliſh was <hi>Paul</hi> to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate thoſe Hereticks, that is, in this new canting Language, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them; if it was lawful for <hi>Paul</hi> to perſecute and moleſt them for their faith and conſcience, it was lawful for them to perſecute and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate him; and what a diſturbance might this cauſe in the Church? Fooliſh Politicians; the profeſſion of the Goſpel in truth and ſincerity, looks not at our own Intereſt in the World, but expects perſecution; teaching men to deny themſelves, to forſake all, their goods, their peace, their lives, were not this as politick an Argument in a Corporation, <q>where Officers are Annual: [Be favourable to drunkards and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane perſons in this your year, leſt one of them get into place next year, and perſecute you: It is for your Intereſt, leſt you lay a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of perſecution, to your ſelves, or your poſterity; for if it be lawful for you to exerciſe coercive power over others, by the ſame rule of reaſon, it will be lawful for others to perſecute you.] 2. Say the ſame for the Proteſtant Intereſt abroad; [If we perſecute m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of their Religion here, they will perſecute ours there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> If be ſhall ſay, there is not the ſame reaſon in matters civil, as in Religion; I ſhall choak him firſt by a Scripture Inſtance; <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was a prudent man, but he had not learned the Jeſuites politicks: He uſed coercive power towards the Heathen Merchants (as well as his own Nations) in a matter of Religion, the <hi>profanation of the Sabbath;</hi> threatning to lay them by the heels, if they brought any more <hi>Wares</hi> to ſell, on that day: How imprudently with reſpect to the Jewiſh Intereſt abroad! Did he not lay a foundation of perſecution of his Country-men, in their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in that, or ſome other point of their Religion? Secondly, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute his policy, by Scripture reaſon: The Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of <q>God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</q> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.] Therefore, he muſt either ſay, that it is not evil, for an heretical ſeducer to deſtroy the ſubjects ſouls, or elſe the Magiſtrate muſt uſe coercive power to reſtrain and puniſh ſuch; let his Intereſt be what it will, at home or abroad. In a word, there is as great a diſtance between perſecution, and proſecution, as between innocency, and wickedneſs, truth and error; and ſurely both ought not to enjoy the ſame priviledges, ſhall truth have but a Toleration, as well as error? He muſt therefore make this <q>conſequence (the foundation of his error) good; [It is lawful for truth and innocency, to preſecute error and wickedneſs. <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is lawful, by the ſame reaſon, for error and wickedneſs, to perſecute truth and innocency] or be ſhews himſelf a very Sophiſter,</q> Cheater, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ducer, and that he hath done ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ntly, in all his reaſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IF this little diſcourſe, for removing the falſe foundations of</hi> Englands <hi>Settlement, find favour and acceptance with thee; expect ſhortly (if God permit) another like it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ying down, and fixing the true and ſolid Foundations of its Settlement,</hi> Righteouſneſs, <hi>and</hi> Religion; <hi>together with the true and many cauſes of our ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g unſettlement:</hi> Fare well.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43574:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
